companies are driven by money so putting
a price on carbon emissions should
encourage businesses to stop polluting
right that's exactly what carbon markets
were designed to do reduce emissions by
charging polluters but so far they
haven't achieved that aim here's
[Music]
why towards the end of the 1980s America
had a problem for years its power
stations have been emitting large
amounts of sulfur dioxide which is
falling back to Earth as acid rain
causing harm to plants aquatic animals
and
infrastructure but there was no
incentive for the power plants to stop
emitting sulfur dioxide weather warnings
and acid rain alert is
ineff so in 1990 the American government
launched an experiment passing Law to
force polluters to pay for their
emissions by establishing a new kind of
Market governed by a system called cap
and
trade 8 years later acid rain levels
over large regions in eastern America
have fallen by 20% and a new way of
cutting emissions was
born in
1997 the international climate change
treaty known as the Kyoto Protocol
suggested app applying the concept of
cap and trade to
carbon in the years that followed
different countries and regions set up
their own carbon
markets many of these use cap and trade
and this is how it
works a government sets a cap on the
amount of CO2 that can be emitted by an
industry it splits the cap into permits
and either gives or sells these permits
to firms if a company doesn't use up
with of its allowance it can sell what
it doesn't need if it needs more permits
it can buy them from those with spares
each year the cap gets stricter and the
shrinking pool of permits gets more
expensive The Genius of c and trade
systems when they're done properly is
that they both use a stick and a carrot
that gives them an incentive to innovate
to get cleaner and cleaner it provides
that carrot for Innovation and that
trading mechanism the magic of the
market unleashes those Animal Spirits in
favor of
decarbonization while regulation can
introduce a new industry standard it
doesn't give firms an incentive to cut
emissions below a certain
level but a carbon Market creates a race
in which companies are motivated to cut
emissions as fast as they
can the more they cut emissions the
fewer permits they have to buy and the
more excess they have to
sell so in theory in a cap and trade
market carbon dioxide emissions should
fall but in reality they've continued to
rise because incentives only work if
they're big
enough now carbon markets are great in
theory but in
practice we run into a problem carbon
prices have been far too low to motivate
change that's needed to decarbonize the
world economy
according to Joseph stiglets and
Nicholas Stern two economists in order
to meet the Paris agreement goal of
limiting global warming to 2° above
pre-industrial levels the price of
carbon worldwide needs to be between 50
and $100 per ton by
2030 however the majority of carbon
prices still remain far below that
figure what's more even if carbon is
priced appropriately the fines for ex
seeding permitted levels are sometimes
ineffectively low in the EU a fine can
be as low as1 EUR per excess turn
considering that's not much more than
the price of a permit it's hardly a
deterrent and that's if firms even get
caught now in theory uh Regulators
enforce carbon prices and permits but in
practice it can be very challenging
there's measurement problems direct
emissions versus indirect emissions uh
there's question questions of cheating
for example you find in most markets
around the world enforcement is lacks
and punishment is not great and even if
some markets adopt effective deterrence
the ones next door may not if you look
globally you have mindboggling variety
of rules systems enforcement mechanisms
and so if you're a company that's based
in multiple countries divisions of your
company making the same product in the
same way will face a mindboggling
patchwork of rules regulations that
differ
worse than that you have leakage among
these markets as well the direct result
of this patch wck of systems is known as
carbon
leakage a business or an industry
relocates from an area with high
environmental regulations to somewhere
where the rules are more relaxed which
means it can avoid having to pay for its
carbon
emissions but these problems have
Solutions the role of Regulation is
important because absent regulation
nobody would pay for carbon emissions or
pay a penalty for emitting carbon so
almost by definition government has to
create the market set the rules enforce
penalties set a carbon cap for example
the maximum amount a company or industry
can emit if governments limited the
number of permits it would drive their
price up setting a minimum price that
rises over time would mean the price
would never fall too low and governments
could enforce more more stringent
deterrence for potential rule
Breakers getting serious about
regulating carbon markets really
involves Regulators making it clear to
Industry that they will not tolerate
cheating they will not tolerate leakage
or obfuscation and ultimately that they
will hold corporate Executives to
account for their carbon emissions I
think we're getting there particularly
in the European Union we're seeing much
more seriousness that this is not a
frivolous greenwashing exercise nudge
nudge wink w but rather that this is as
serious as safety or other regulations
this is not yet the case in many other
parts of the
world it would help if the world had
more integrated carbon markets but as
that's unlikely to happen in the short
term one solution to help prevent carbon
leakage is a border
tax the EU has recently proposed to tax
the carbon emitted in Goods produced
outside its carbon Market importers
would have to pay the same amount as if
the goods have been made in the EU
meaning it wouldn't be any cheaper to
Source goods from a region with less
regulation if we're going to get serious
about dealing with climate change within
the next few years we must achieve
something like a global carbon price and
some form of harmonization amongst
economies now we're getting to something
like momentum in this direction the Big
Kahuna is China because it's such a
indust industrial powerhouse it's so
carbon intensive if it doesn't get
serious and work with other economies to
harmonize carbon pricing and carbon
trading systems then most of the world's
efforts will probably be undermined by
the fact that countries like China are
producing heavily carbon intensive goods
and we'll see multinationals shifting
production to those places even more
than they have in the
past as climate change has moved up the
political agenda governments are
starting to improve how their carbon
markets
work since 2019 the EU has been taking
steps to reduce the number of permits it
hands out partly as a result carbon
prices in the EU are now hitting record
highs of over €60 per ton carbon prices
in other markets are also Rising as
Regulators look at ways to make them
more
effective if it seems that money can be
made other countries might create their
own markets
we have seen just in the last 12 to 18
months a dramatic takeoff in carbon
markets this is a really exciting time
for people who believe that there is a
good marriage between public policy and
regulators and markets and
innovators if prices stay high enough
helped by commitments from governments
and Regulators then Greener industrial
processes would become more
attractive and carbon markets could
start to achieve their original goal of
help helping to decarbonize the
world I'm VJ VIIs Warren The Economist
Global energy and climate Innovation
Editor to keep up to date with all of
our climate change coverage please click
on the link thanks for watching and
don't forget to subscribe
[Music]